US President Donald Trump wants to
impose a 10% global tariff on America's
trading partners after the Supreme Court
struck out most of his previous levies
as illegal. Trump said the 6 to3 ruling
left him deeply disappointed and accused
the Supreme Court of being quote swayed
by foreign interests. The president has
vowed to deploy new methods to impose
tariffs that will not require approval,
including a sweeping new duty on all
foreign trading partners. ability to
both regulate trade and impose tariffs.
>> W's Misha Kodowski joins me now from
Washington. Misha, you have been
following this story throughout the day
as expected. This decision did not sit
well with the president. What else did
he say at the press briefing?
>> You're right. President Trump lashed out
after the Supreme Court blocked his
emergency law tariffs. And now he plans
to sign an executive order imposing a
10% tariff on all countries replacing
the tariffs uh that uh were struck down.
He praised the conservative justices who
dissented Thomas Alo and Kavanaaugh as
brave and pro-America. At the same time,
he blasted the Supreme Court majority as
partisan and unpatriotic and even said
that their families should be ashamed.
The president added that they're bowing
to political pressure and foreign
interests and announced he will not
stop. Let's take a listen.
>> Foreign countries that have been ripping
us off for years are ecstatic. They're
so happy
and they're dancing in the streets, but
they won't be dancing for long. That I
can assure you. But other alternatives
will now be used to replace the ones
that the court incorrectly rejected. We
have an alternatives.
>> What alternatives does he really have
and how wide reaching would they be?
>> Well, again, President Trump announced
plans to impose uh these 10% global
tariffs under section 122 in addition to
existing tariffs. The US has never used
this authority before and the tariffs
are scheduled to start next week. This
section 122 gives the president the
power to put a tariff on imports up to
15% for up to 150 days. It's meant to
help if the United States is losing too
much money in trade uh with other
countries or if the dollar is in trouble
after 150 days. The president needs
congressional approval to keep the
tariffs going and that's in question.
sure that they did not mean to do.
>> Now, has Trump offered any explanation
on how he plans to handle the hundreds
of billions of dollars already collected
under these tariffs that have now been
ruled unlawful?
>> Well, not much clarity here, at least at
least publicly. The administration did
not lay out a clear settled plan for
what happens to the money already
collected. President Trump says tariff
refunds issue could end in courts for
years and years. And the Supreme Court
majority opinion did not specify what
should happen to the more than roughly
$130 billion already collected. And mind
you, this number is uh uh not settled.
So it leaves the refund question quite
open. The National Retail Federation
here in the United States and the major
anti-tariff coalition are both calling
for full, fast, and automatic refunds.
So, expect more litigations.
>> There's Washington correspondent Misha
Kodovski. Thank you so much for your
coverage today.
>> We want to take a closer look now at
these developments and what they mean
for international trade and bring in
Marco Forion. He heads the advisory firm
the Chartered Institute of Export and
International Trade. Welcome to DW. Now,
one set of tariffs is ruled illegal.
Another is slapped right on. How is this
10% different from the so-called
Liberation Day levies?
>> Well, it's a it's a different nuance and
it's more wide ranging and it's
short-term. The Liberation Day tariffs
were meant to be uh for until they were
negotiated away. These tariffs uh the
10% are for a maximum of 150 days. But I
think what we're going to see now is a
very muscular approach to negotiation by
the Trump administration with uh third
countries because they're going to
launch now a series of trade
investigations with a threat of much
higher tariffs under the uh rules that
the Supreme Court have said are legal.
Mhm.
>> In layman's terms, what will all of this
mean for global trade? What will be the
immediate impact?
>> The reality is we are going we're seeing
a continuation of what's been happening
to global trade for the past three or
four years. ongoing instability,
uncertainty and disruption which means
price pressures for the consumers uh and
the risk of availability uh and the
shrinkflation for uh people on the
shelves. This is just another reason for
uh businesses particularly those in the
EU to look at a multissource multimarket
approach. We cannot be dependent on a
single supply chain or a single nation
and we cannot be dependent on a single
nation as our marketplace.
>> Yeah. Now that these old terrorists have
been declared illegal, can importers
reclaim the duties they paid since April
of last year.
>> Yes. But and that's the problem with so
much in international trade. uh so yes
they should be entitled to uh reclaim
what has been judged to be illegal uh
tariff payments however the process for
doing that and the fact that this is
going to be tied up now in a whole
bureaucratic process means that there's
no clarity uh on this and I think the
best thing that that companies can do is
to uh hold fast and wait until a little
bit more clarity comes because uh it's
very it's very obvious that what
President Trump is trying to do is to
disrupt global supply chains to disrupt
the global multilateral order and impose
an America first program of activities
and we've seen the impact of that. We've
seen disruption to supply chains. We've
seen uh businesses facing uncertainty.
And as a result, big businesses,
companies like Stalantis and others have
made decisions to invest in the US to
build their capabilities in the US
because of these original set of
tariffs. And I'm certain that President
Trump and the administration in
Washington have no intent on leaving
taking their foot off the pedal,
releasing the pressure uh because they
want more of that type of investment in
the US to grow the manufacturing base in
the US.
>> So do you think it's actually paying off
because the intent of these tariffs
under the America first umbrella was the
revival of American manufacturing. Is
that really happening?
Well, first we've seen billions being
generated as a result of the tariffs. Uh
we have seen huge announcements from
companies like Stellantis and Ro and
others that they are going to invest
significantly to grow manufacturing
capability uh in the US. uh but the the
transition between what have been
decades of decline in US manufacturing
and the uh the impact of those uh
investment announcements there's a lag
uh so what we've seen over the last
quarter uh in fact the last half a year
is a decline in uh US manufacturing uh
uh output we've seen an increase in the
trade deficit and these are factors that
the Trump administration will be taking
a long hard look at as They seek to
pursue that America first program.
>> Tariffs, and we've heard it many times
are Trump's favorite word that zooming
out a bit. How big a blow is this ruling
for his overall economic strategy that
was so heavily reliant on tariffs?
>> Well, anyone who listened to his
response this evening could see he's
really angry at what happened. However,
I don't think it was unexpected and the
fact that they've come forward
instantaneously with a new approach, the
10% tariff for the next 150 days and
they will be uh launching uh trade
investigations on a whole bunch of uh
products, a whole bunch of uh countries
uh to try and exert more pressure and to
apply differential tariffs uh on them.
And I'm sure over the coming weeks and
months there will be new approaches to
impose tariffs, put pressure on
countries because what he's doing is
using trade and tariffs as a
geopolitical lever. And he wants to
secure bilateral trade arrangements to
the advantage of the US, to the
advantage of US consumers, to the
advantage of US manufacturing. None of
that changes. The way he goes about it
may shift slightly. The legal basis for
his approach may shift slightly, but
what we can be sure of is that he is
absolutely cleareyed and determined to
impose that America first agenda.
>> What a time to be a trade adviser. We
just spoke to one of them, Marco
Foriona, director general of the
Chartered Institute of Export and
International Trade. Thank you so much
for all those insights.
Before the German reaction to the
Supreme Court decision, our chief
political editor, Mika Kufna, caught up
with the CDU lawmaker and foreign policy
spokesperson Jurgen Hhat at the party's
conference.
>> Jurgen Hart, is this ruling a gamecher
for the way Donald Trump can conduct
international politics? too early to
judge on and I think also from outside
it's difficult for us to um comment a
decision of the Supreme Court in a
sovereign democratic country
constitutional questions are always uh
in a core of uh the sovereignity of a
state but looking to that what might be
the consequences I think about that
Donald Trump's tax policy is very much
based on the fact that he has a huge
income from tariffs and uh that the
trade relations of US to other regions
like European Union or India for example
are very much um driven by uh the tariff
system regime and therefore um I think
we also have to think about what is the
consequence for us uh maybe a new
momentum in trade negotiations with US
uh and uh also new momentum for some
parts of the business uh for their
future business in US or here in Europe.
>> Does this change the way you perceive
Donald Trump can act? Now there's a
court ruling. Do you think he will stick
to it?
>> Uh I think Donald Trump's uh um was very
much aware of not to have a um
defeat in uh in on on the Supreme Court
and not to be uh a majority against him
in the Congress. and uh there was a
majority close to a majority against him
in the visa question in the Senate and
now there's a decision of the Supreme
Court. I think he has to think about
what are the consequences for its
politics up to the midterm elections but
we will see Americans will uh take the
right decisions and right consequences
of that what happened today. Thank you
very much.